<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A golden bell, and a pomgranate A sermon preached, at the visitation in Canterbury. 7. of Aprill. 1624. By Mr. Alexander Vdny, Bachelor in Diuinitie, chaplaine to his Maiestie in ordinary, and minister of Hauking in Kent.</title>
            <author>Udny, Alexander, minister of Hauking in Kent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118896</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854103</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14197)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1119:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A golden bell, and a pomgranate A sermon preached, at the visitation in Canterbury. 7. of Aprill. 1624. By Mr. Alexander Vdny, Bachelor in Diuinitie, chaplaine to his Maiestie in ordinary, and minister of Hauking in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Udny, Alexander, minister of Hauking in Kent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] and I[ohn] N[orton] for Anthony Vphill, and are to be sold at the signe of the white Lyon, in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:1"/>
            <p>A GOLDEN BELL. AND A POMGRANATE.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached, at the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Canterbury.</hi> 7. of <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1624.</p>
            <p>By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ALEXANDER VDNY, Bachelor in Diuinitie, Chaplaine to his Maieſtie in Ordinary, and Miniſter of <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Labour till I come. <bibl>
                  <hi>LVKE 19.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GREGO. lib. 2. Epiſt. 39.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <hi>Quod pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fecto negotium, tunc vere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s agi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſi viuendo &amp; loquendo proxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> and <hi>I. N.</hi> for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Anthony Vphill,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the white Lyon, in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:2"/>
            <head>REVERENDISSIMO PATRI ET DOMINO, SVO VNICE, COLENDO <hi>GEORGIO</hi> CANTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arienſi Archiepiſcopo <hi>totius Angli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Primati.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>QVas animi Dono faetus (Ampliſsime Praeſul)</l>
               <l>Pignora perpetui Debita amoris erunt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tu modo quae voueo, facili cape munera Dextra,</l>
               <l>Nil meruere vltra, in meliora forent.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Celſitudini veſtrae Humillime addictus. ALEXANDER VDNEYVS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:3"/>
            <head>A GOLDEN BELL, AND A POMGRANATE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>COL. 4.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> the Miniſterie which thou haſt receiued of the Lord, ſee that thou fulfill it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat is the Myſterie of godlineſſe, which is, God is manifeſt in the fleſh<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note>, Great, becauſe the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hid ſince the beginning of the World, and from all Ages; but now is made manifeſt vnto his Saints<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 1.26. Luke 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: This manifeſtation was and is by the Spirit in the Word; then opened hee their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that they might vnderſtand the Scriptures, which is a Lanthorne vnto our feet, &amp; a light vnto our pathes<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 119.105.</note>; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this light, we dwell in the land of the ſhadow of death,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 4.16.</note> both in ſinne and ignorance; therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light<note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note>; This light doeth ſhine to him, whoſe name is in the white ſtone, which no man knoweth, ſauing hee that receiueth it<note n="f" place="margin">Reu. 2 17.</note>; This knowledge is giuen to him, that can take the little booke out of the Angels hand, and eate it vp, hereby able to Propheſie among the people, and Nations, and Tongues, and to many Kings<note n="g" place="margin">Reu. 10.11.</note>; For this
<pb facs="tcp:19510:4"/> cauſe it is, that <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth, open mine eies,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 119.18.</note> that I may ſee the wonders of thy Law.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is the Commandement of the chiefe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of our profeſsion, and Biſhop of our ſoules the Lord Ieſus (beloued in him)<note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that wee ſhould ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for his Teſtimonie, and our owne ſaluation<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 39.5. Non repoſtores aut ſerriui colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos vel ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſos mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murateres, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ram hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lem &amp; vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r cognoſcendae &amp; ample <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de veritatis cupidaeus. <hi>Mui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> lus</hi> in 5. <hi>Ioh.</hi>
               </note>: wee ſhould not then negligently, or ſuperſtitiouſly ſearch the Scriptures to cauell thereby, but with a holy, and humble deſire, to know and embrace the ſimple trueth</p>
            <p>And now being my courſe to Preach at this time, before this ſolemne aſſembly, and publike Conuocation of the Miniſterie, I haue ſought, and red in the Booke of the Lord, where I might finde a Text, ſhort, ſententious, and ſitting, principally for the Miniſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, exhorting all in a word, and euery one as it were by his owne name, to holy, and full knowledge, faith, and diligence in his vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and I haue found theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Lord<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Kodeth la Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>era <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urion.</note>, which was grauen on the high Prieſts Miter, as ſignets are grauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for in the man of God, what is required but Holineſſe in ſpirit, in ſoule, in ſpeach, in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in all things, Holineſſe to the Lord, and vpon the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels of the horſes, holineſſe to the Lord, yea, the very pots in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſhall be holineſſe vnto the Lord of hoſtes,<note n="m" place="margin">Zach. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> holineſſe is Chriſts marke, like the ſigne <hi>Thau,</hi> vpon the foreheads of them that mourne, for the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he done in the middeſt of the Citie<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach. 8.4.</note>.</p>
            <p>And I haue found a line, and a golden reed, wherewith I intend to mete the Temple of God, and to meaſure the Citie withall<note n="o" place="margin">Reuel. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.15. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lled <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hacte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idda ſuu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> menſores.</hi>
               </note>. In the Epiſtle to the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> theſe words, (<hi>And ſay to</hi> Archippus) for as the firſt Scripture comprehended all the worke of the Miniſterie in one word, Holineſſe; ſo this Text, comprehends the ſame in one word, of power, and authoritie, commanding euery one, in one, fulfill this diſpenſation of God, which is giuen me vnto you ward, to fulfill the word of God<note n="p" place="margin">Col. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note>.</p>
            <p>For what is it, to bee a good Miniſter of the Lord, but to fulfill, and end perfectly, the worke of miniſtration, and diſpenſation of the Goſpel of his graces, that wee may bee
<pb facs="tcp:19510:4"/> bold before God, and man, Angels, and our conſcience,<note place="margin">Micha 3.8.</note> with <hi>Micha</hi> to ſay, I am full of power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of iudgement, and of ſtrength, to declare vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> his tranſgreſsion, and to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> their ſinne;<note n="q" place="margin">Act. 23.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And with <hi>Paul,</hi> I haue liued in all good conſcience before God, vntill this day, that we may all ſay ſo, I ſay, O generation, ſee ye the word of the Lord<note n="r" place="margin">Iere. 2.31.</note>.</p>
            <p>The holy and perfect worke of the Miniſterie,<note place="margin">Holineſſe.</note> and maner thereof, are by theſe two Scriptures comprehended in two words, Holineſſe, and Fulneſſe, or Holy Fulneſſe, or Full Holineſſe; would y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then deſire a better Scripture for this time, which may bee called the Miniſters Text, then one of thoſe two, or both in one, making ſo ſweete an harmonie, like two parts of Muſicke ſet together, to praiſe the Lord, in whom dwelleth all fulneſſe, whereupon I ſhall deſcant God willing, according to the commandment of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without any diſcord; and that it may found alſo well in your eares, as it did to the <hi>Colloſsians,</hi> and their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, let mee craue of you, as hee of them, that ye would pray for mee, that God would open vnto mee the doore of vtterance, that I may ſpeake the Myſterie of Chriſt fully.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle hauing laide downe the foundation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, by Chriſt in his perſon and office,<note place="margin">Coheſion.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Colo. 1.14. Colo. 2.1.</note> whereby we are reconſciled, then hee doeth diſwade from Eronious Doctrine, hee doeth exhort vnto Chriſtian conuerſation,<note place="margin">Colo. 3.1.2.</note> that wee ſet our affections on things which are aboue, and hauing added ſalutations to his friends in loue, in the end doeth exhort the <hi>Colloſsians,</hi> that they ſhould admoniſh <hi>Archippus</hi> to be faithfull in the worke of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The argument of this Text, is this; in a ſhort ſumme, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> after <hi>Epaphras</hi> his declaration, what ſtate and condition the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> and their Miniſters were in, in reſpect of Chriſtian Religion, writ their admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and exhortation from <hi>Rome,</hi> to them both, that they ſhould ſtand faſt, and grow ſtill in the knowledge, and vſe of the Goſpel againſt all corruption, to the Miniſterie indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, and to all vnder the name of one, that the <hi>Colloſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> earneſtly, and yet gentlely in theſe words, admoniſh
<pb facs="tcp:19510:5"/> 
               <hi>Archippus</hi> to hold his eye, and his hand, vpon the Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel faithfully towards them, which he hath receiued of the Lord, a worthy thing, in credit whereof he muſt giue an account as Miniſter, by whom they muſt grow from faith, to faith, who hath called him, and giuen him an eye to ſee, and a hand to feele, and who will reward him according to his ſeruice, Damnation, or Saluation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two parts of this T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t</note>The order and method of this Text, is in too princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt an admonition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the reaſon of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>The admonition that <hi>Archippus,</hi> and in him other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Citie, bee wiſe, and faithfull in doing their office, in teſtifying the Goſpel of Gods grace fully.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Reaſon.</note>The reaſon, becauſe the Lord Ieſus hath made him a Miniſter and diſpoſer of the ſame, to whom hee muſt giue an account of his Miniſtration, and bee rewarded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion there is ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulars</note>In the admonition, wee haue ſixe grounds to conſider: Firſt, who giueth it, <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Timothie</hi> by writing, <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras</hi> being priuie to the ſame, whom they commend as faithfull: Chap. 4.13. and the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> by the word, at their commandement.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, who is the perſon admoniſhed, <hi>Archippus,</hi> one of the ordinary Miniſters, reſident among them.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, what is the manner of the admonition, not ſeuere, albeit ſeuere, but gentle, ſhort, and publike.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, what time this admoniſhion was giuen, when falſe teachers entered in amongſt them, and therefore had neede.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, what things are principally required, wiſedome, and ſtrength, with vſe and practiſe, of both Seeing, and feeling.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, who are Meſſengers, and what is their credit, <hi>Tichicus,</hi> and <hi>Oneſsimus,</hi> their credit is to declare <hi>Pauls</hi> eſtate, and to know theirs, and to comfort their Miniſters, and people in the Lord. Chap. 4.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>In the reaſon, euery word containes a moſt ſtrong and
<pb facs="tcp:19510:5"/> mighty argument, arguing the faithfull execution of the Miniſterie in the right manner, all worthy by themſelues to be remembred; in generall is this;</p>
            <p>If <hi>Archippus</hi> be allowed, to haue committed vnto him in credit, the miniſtration of the Goſpel of Gods grace vnto his Church; vpon condition, that beholding, and fulfilling the ſame, to receiue an euerlaſting crowne of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if not, to haue no part with him; then he muſt See, and fulfill his miniſtration.</p>
            <p>But hee is allowed of the Lord,<note place="margin">The ſumme of the reaſon.</note> to haue committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, the miniſtration of Gods grace to his Church; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition, that ſeeing, and fulfilling his Miniſterie, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue an euerlaſting Crowne of Glory, if not, to haue no part with him; therefore <hi>Archippus</hi> muſt See, and fulfill his miniſtration fully.</p>
            <p>The particular arguments are theſe.<note place="margin">The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are ſixe,</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the conſideration of <hi>Archippus,</hi> his inſufficiencie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in him the receiuer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the authoritie of the Lord, the deliuerer. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the incomprehenſible worthineſſe, of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Goſpel, the thing receiued, whereof he is a Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the word of office, miniſtration, or diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, the conſideration of the Church, bought with the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> blood of Ieſus, to the which hee muſt Miniſter, and diſpoſe the ſecrets of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, the reward of his miniſtration, at the Lords hand, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Saluation, or Perdition, according as hee doeth Miniſter, Well, or Ill: This is the ſum &amp; order of this Text, ſhort, but full of matter; ye ſee the interpretation, and vſe doeth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe things, in this maner parted, &amp; gathered together orderly, and ſhortly muſt be laide open againe, before our eyes, in the light of the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes cannot bee ſeene, nor handled, that we may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and handle the ſame, take for nought, and without money.</p>
            <p>The Lord open our eyes to See, and ſtrengthen our hands to feele the diſpenſation of the Goſpel of Chriſt, whereof we are Miniſters.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:6"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe ence.</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> was at this time in <hi>Rome</hi> an old man, and in bands, which commendes his admonition the more, and had not viſited them of <hi>Colloſſe,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea;</hi> which makes him the more carefull of them. Chap. 2.1. And namely, praying for them continually: verſe 3. and in writing to them, and their Miniſters in doing their dutie towards God, and one another; It is profitable for vs to conſider <hi>Pauls</hi> age, and that which is more, his bonds and captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ch iſts priſoner; for in the next verſe, he bids remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his bonds, and he requeſts <hi>Philemon</hi> to receiue <hi>Onoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> againe, becauſe it is old <hi>Paul,</hi> and Chriſts priſoner that exhorteth him.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>1</label> Hereby wee learne, what Miniſters are moſt ſitting to exhort and admoniſh others, to behold, and fulfill their Miniſterie, <hi>viz.</hi> they that are caref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, zealous, deuout, old, graue, conſtant vnto bonds, ſuffering as well the heate, as the cold of the day, in the labour of the Lords vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde.</p>
            <p>Certainely, the Church is more bound to <hi>Pauls</hi> bonds, then to his libertie; not onely in reſpect of his writing, but alſo in reſpect of the example of his famous bonds, euen in <hi>Ceſaeres</hi> Pallace, and all other places, which made many of brethr n in the Lord,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to preach the Goſpel boldly.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ioyneth with him <hi>Timothie,</hi> a man greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the Scriptures, and not to bee deſpiſed for his youth; <hi>Epaphras</hi> was priuie to this admonition, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in the Citie, to the end it might be the more willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeyed, being by many, and that ſo worthily, giuen firſt in writing, and then in words by his owne congregation.</p>
            <p>Here we may learne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more, and the more worthy they bee that admoniſh the greater is their admonition, and ought to be the more acceptable, ſuch as is the admonition of a generall Aſſembly, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nod, Presb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terie, or as by this Viſitation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſi.</note>Moreouer, it is the <hi>Colloſsians,</hi> that muſt giue this admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to their Miniſter, that they may bee faithfull in the miniſtration of the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pel towardes them: <hi>Colloſſe</hi> is a Citie of <hi>Phrigia,</hi> not farre from <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicus,</hi> and <hi>Hierapolis,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19510:6"/> and therefore, <hi>Epaphras</hi> might the more conueniently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his loue, for all three.</p>
            <p>In that the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> are required to admoniſh their <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>3</label> owne Miniſter, to bee diligent in his calling, giueth thus to learne.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as there ſhould bee knowledge in the Prieſts lipes, and practiſe in his hands, ſo there ſhould bee zeale in the peoples hearts, to ſeeke it at his mouth, and if he be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, to deſire him to be diligent in the worke of the Lord: but alas, if wee haue an euill will to preach,<note place="margin">Note.</note> they haue a worſe will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o heare; for they thinke God is beholding to them, if they come to the Sermon in the forenoone, albeit they ſerue the deuill in the afternoone, and all the weeke following.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the people muſt not contend with their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, for reproouing of them for their ſinnes;<note place="margin">Hoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.4.</note> like the people that reprooued, and contended with the Prieſt of God,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8.7.</note> therefore God ſaid vnto <hi>Samuel,</hi> they haue not caſt thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but they haue caſt me away: Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Exod. 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Lord hath heard your murmurings which ye murmure againſt him; therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Korah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num 16.11. verſe 33. 2. King. 2.14. 2. Chro. 26.12</note> thou and thy company are gathered againſt the Lord, and in the end were ſwallowed vp quicke into hell: two Beares came out of the Forreſt, and ſlew fourtie and two children that mocked <hi>Eliſha;</hi> ſo was the Captaines with their fifties, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed with fire from the heauens: and while King <hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> was wroth with the Prieſts, the Lord ſtrooke him with Leproſie: This example of the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> admoniſhing their Miniſters, makes againſt the flockes, that thinke it is not good manners to admoniſh their Paſtors, and yet they are not ſcrupulus, to traduce him behind his backe to others.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> why <hi>Paul</hi> writ not directly to <hi>Archippus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to behold, and fulfill his Miniſterie, as hee did at the ſame time to him and <hi>Philemon,</hi> about a matter of leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; namely, the receiuing againe of <hi>Oneſsimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The reaſon.</note> bearer hereof, becauſe of their faith, loue, ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, and ſtedfaſtneſſe in all good workes: as Chap. 1.4. and 2. chap. 5.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> the admonition of his owne Congregation
<pb facs="tcp:19510:7"/> would preuaile with him, and that Paſtor, and flocke, might mutually admoniſh one another, as they muſt pray one for another, proceeding of loue.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>4</label> Fourthly, who ſhould exhort the Miniſter to doe his miniſtration, not the confuſed multitude, but the moſt godly, and moſt learned.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>5</label> Fiftly, perſeuerance in the Goſpel, and vſe thereof is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in Prieſt, and People, the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> had truely heard, and learned the grace of God, yet <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> and <hi>Epaphras,</hi> ceaſed not to pray for them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them, to require <hi>Archippus,</hi> to bee diligent in his Miniſterie: other vertues without perſeuerance, auaileth nothing.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>6</label> Sixtly, the greater perrill the people are in, being drawen away as a prey; like as the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> were at this time:<note place="margin">Numb. 8.24.</note> Chap. 2.8. The more carefull the Miniſter muſt bee, <hi>Ad militandum militiam in Miniſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> like the Leuites in the Miniſterie of the Tabernacle; but wee are moſt careleſſe in the greateſt danger, who ſeeth not, but we ſee not.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>7</label> Seuenthly, the neceſsitie of the Miniſterie, in all the fulneſſe thereof; the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> had the Scriptures of the old and new Teſtaments exſtant, this Epiſtle, and that from <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which they are commanded to read, and cauſe to be read vnto others; Yet they muſt ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> See and fulfill thy miniſtration: would to God, this admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were taken to heart, in theſe dayes wherein we liue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The perſon admoniſhed.</note>Now wee come to the ſecond point, to wit, who is the Perſon admoniſhed, that is <hi>Archippus,</hi> a Phrigian, an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Miniſter among the <hi>Colloſsians,</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> fellow-labourer.</p>
            <p>Vpon this we worke firſt, that particular admonition of Miniſters is needfull, that they that doe well, may better doe, and they that doe euill, may amend; for the Harueſt is great, and beſides that, the labourers are few, and amongſt theſe few, there bee few faithfull, beholding, and fulfilling their Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as there is nothing hid, that ſhall not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed,
<pb facs="tcp:19510:7"/> but more the neglect of dutie in the Miniſterie, <hi>Paul</hi> was in <hi>Italy,</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> in priſon, <hi>Archippus</hi> in <hi>Phrigia,</hi> at <hi>Colloſse,</hi> ſo great a ſpace of Sea and Land betwixt; yet <hi>Paul</hi> knew that <hi>Archippus</hi> had neede of this admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a Miniſter is like a Citie vpon a hill, and like a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in a candleſticke, and as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, Trueth, the daughter of God, and of Time, hath ſworne to detect all vice and ſinne, and ſpecially in the Miniſterie, who are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the miniſtration, which they haue receiued of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third point to be conſidered,<note place="margin">The third point in the admonition. Wherein is three things.</note> and that is the forme, and manner of this admonition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſhort; ſecondly, gentle; thirdly, publike: Short, becauſe a word to a wiſeman is ſufficient, few things are be remembred, hee referres the particular admonition, to the Epiſtle written from <hi>Laodicca,</hi> that is, the firſt to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie,</hi> which he commanded them to read, and leaues the ample declaration thereof to the <hi>Colloſsians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Gentle, becauſe hee did well: for they that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> doe not well, muſt bee commanded with authoritie; <hi>Paul</hi> be-ſought <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.3.</note> but <hi>Timothie,</hi> muſt command with power, and reprooue them that haue need of ſeueritie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Publike,<note place="margin">Tims 2.3.15.</note> becauſe it muſt be read in the Church of <hi>Colloſse,</hi> and <hi>Laodicca,</hi> verſe 16. Wee obſerue, if <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus, Timothie,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> receiued publike admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and willingly learned: it becommeth vs much more, who liue in this laſt declining age of the World, where the power of the Goſpel is almoſt turned to the libertie of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Paul</hi> ſent this admonition with <hi>Tichicus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The fourth point in the admonition.</note> a faithfull Miniſter, and fellow ſeruant in the Lord, and <hi>Oneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus</hi> a beloued brother to comfort their hearts, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his eſtate, and to know theirs, as in all his Epiſtles he chuſeth godly, and honeſt meſſengers.</p>
            <p>Firſt, obſerue prayer, writing, and liuely voyce, is too <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>1</label> little to ſtrengthen vs in trouble.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that wee giue not ſo much, as the bearing, or <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation. </seg>2</label> carrying of Holy things vnto dogs, and ſwine, as woefull
<pb facs="tcp:19510:8"/> exſperience doeth let vs ſee this day, yet precious are they vnto God, and muſt be in our eyes whoſe they are.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fift ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition.</note>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly, what time this admonition was giuen, when falſe teachers were entered in amongſt them: as the 2. Chap. 8. verſe. By this is a true Miniſter knowne, if hee be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the greateſt danger, when Gods people are like to be carried into captiuitie, either of the body or mind. I pray God make vs thus faithfull, for I feare the time is at hand, that a faithfull Miniſter ſhall be knowne from an hireling.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fift point in two parts.</note>Now followeth the laſt thing in the admonition, in two words, behold, and fulfill, which are actions of the eye, and hand, of the body properly two members, principally in Gods houſe: Miniſters, and Paſtors, Ciuill, and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, muſt bee whole, ſound, and able, the eye, and the hand; the eye to ſee, and foreſee, what things are profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and what are hurtfull for the flocke, the arme to ſaue and defend the ſame, for they that want them, or haue them vnable, or mutilate, are vnmeete for the office of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, defending, or gouerning of others; but theſe are borrowed and tranſlated wordes, from the body to the minde; by the eye is vnderſtood wiſedome, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; by the arme, might, ſtrength, and power; in the ſame ſenſe it is taken. <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.17. O i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oll ſhepheard that leaueth the flocke,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.17.</note> the ſword ſhall bee vpon his arme, and vpon his right eye; his arme ſhall bee dried, and his right eye ſhall be vtterly darkened; <hi>Archippus</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by <hi>Paul, Timothie</hi> and his flocke, that he be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his calling, with the power of godly wiſdome, which he hath now receiued of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To ſee, it is taken foure wayes.</note>By ſeeing, is vnderſtood foure things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we ſee by our fleſhly eyes. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Secondly, to ſee, is to vnderſtand, for Chriſt ſaw the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thoughts of his enemies, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, behold the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueritie of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to ſee, is taken for exſperience. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. The waters ſaw thee. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to ſee, is to be watching &amp; carefull. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.36.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth theſe words, of the eye,
<pb facs="tcp:19510:8"/> arme, and hand, ſeeing, and fulfilling,<note place="margin">The reaſon why the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle vſeth theſe figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue words.</note> when they would haue any thing well done: Is, becauſe we remember bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the things we ſee, then the things we heare, and becauſe the ſight is more diuine, and likeſt to the vnderſtanding, and when both our eye, and hand, are vpon our worke together, it proſpers and proceedes well.</p>
            <p>But that wee may ſee,<note place="margin">The ſenſe of ſeeing excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all the reſt in ſixe degree.</note> by this borrowed ſpeech which is worthy to bee conſidered, what excellent practiſe, and vſe of wiſedome, and ſtrength is required in a Miniſter of the Goſpel; and that this admonition may bee the better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in our mindes, which for our mindes ſake is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; let vs conſider, that the ſenſe of ſeeing, is the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of all our wits, and ſenſes, which outwardly perceiue, and how? euen by the true triall of our owne exſperience, and vſe of our outward ſenſes; and therefore the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Thomas</hi> who was hard of beliefe, to ſee, and handle his wounds, and print of the miles; conſider thou that the ſight excelleth all our other ſenſes, in ſixe ſeuerall cauſes, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. <hi>Muſculi in oculi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galen.</note> 
               <hi>ſunt ſex ſecundum vtrunque oculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum habentes, ſubſtractam pinguedinem quibus, actus commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſpiritus commiſſus eſt, perficientis motus etus, per ipſos facti ſunt autem, vt facile circumducantur oculi, quando vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus hue mouere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that our ſight perceiueth things farre off. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, and more of them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, and more exquiſitely. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, and more ſwiftly. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, and vnder no difference. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, and more diuinely. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Farther off, becauſe we ſee the ſtarres of heauen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Many things, becauſe there is nothing almoſt, that wants light, &amp; colour; which are the firſt obiects of the eie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. More exquiſitely, becauſe there is no ſenſe, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues to little, and ſo ſmall differences of things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Swift, or ſooner, becauſe we ſee onely incontinent; wee hezie not, before the ſound come to our eares; and ſmell not, but by blowing out and in our breath.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Manifeſt differences, as all kinde of colours, and
<pb facs="tcp:19510:9"/> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he fiue common ſenſible things, <hi>Magnitudo, immerus, motus, quies, forma,</hi> which it attaines vnto perfectly, for the hand or feeling, attaines not vnto them ſo perfectly; for the hand diſcenres them onely in darkeneſſe, when we may not ſee them with our eyes; but when wee may ſee them, the hand or feeling, is content with it owne obiects, as <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidum, frigidum, humidum, ſiccum, graue, leue, molle, durum, lentum fragile, leue, asperum;</hi> when the eye and the hand worke together, it deceiues all the common ſenſible things, either onely, or chiefely.</p>
            <p n="6">6. More diuinely, becauſe it feeles no paine, nor labour in ſeeing, and onely is like the vnderſtanding of the minde; what ſubtill and deceitfull things are theſe? But yet as Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſsionem lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> diſputing of the ſpaces of time, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prizing, and prayſing God, ſaith, <hi>Vſitata &amp; abdita,</hi> vſuall, and yet hid things, therefore we ſhould all pray with him, <hi>Per Chriſtum obſecro Noli claudere,</hi> wee vſe them continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but know not how, the greater part; but if wee knew, we would remember this admonition the better, and praiſe the Lord the more; the eye of the minde is knowledge, and the hand practiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. The eyes.</note>The eye of the mortall body ſeeth farre off, and ſhall the eye of the immortall ſoule bee purblinde, that it cannot ſee farre off?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. The minde.</note>The eye of the mortall body, ſeeth all things almoſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath giuen all things almoſt, light, and colour to bee ſeene; and ſhall the eye of the immortall ſoule ſee nothing, or few things of many, all viſible by light, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out change of darkeneſſe, and colour without blot of ſtaining?</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The eye of the mortall body, ſeeth exquiſitely, there is not ſo ſmall, or ſo little a thing, but the eye ſeeth it; and ſhall the eye of the immortall ſoule ſee but with a glime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as in a glaſſe, the great and exquiſite things of God?</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The eye of the mortall body, diſcernes all things, and markes their differences, and diuerſitie knowne; and ſhall the eye of the immortall ſoule bee confounded, and not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne things that differ one from another? <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:9"/>
            <p>The eye of the mortall body is not pained, nor pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſeeing, and ſhall the eye of the immortall ſoule thinke it a paine and labour to ſee, till there bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no more time to ſee in? the eye of the immortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath many things to ſee, that it helpes the hand whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it may not feele, albeit the ſenſe of ſeeing be moſt excellent, yet there is ſome defect to bee noted of in our ſight; for when the thing wee ſee is oppoſed to our ſight directly, then the qualitie of that commeth vpon the lynes falling into the Center of our eyes,<note place="margin">Note.</note> the which lynes all directly from euery part, maketh vp one Pyramides, <hi>Cuius conus eſt in pupills, &amp; baſis in re viſa ex quo pates, quod talis Pyramis ex parteres in ſo habet latitudinem, ex parte vero occuli artitudinem:</hi> euen ſo when wee doe contemplate on heauenly things, wee cannot comprehend them, by reaſon of weakeneſſe. Therefore God ſaid vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> thou ſhalt ſee my back parts, but my face thou canſt not ſee and liue: in the ſight of the face, <hi>Noticia eſt perfecta,</hi> but in ſeeing the backe parts, our knowledge is but <hi>modica &amp; confuſa,</hi> our knowledge is but in part &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; therefore a diſtance muſt bee from our ſight, <hi>Secundum aliquam proportionem intra quam non ſubquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſed magis et minus videtur ſecundum modum diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae:</hi> vnto the Saints heauenly things are <hi>occuli propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> to the wicked <hi>remoti,</hi> as the Glutton ſaw <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> a farre off.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Hand hath many things to handle, we heard that it helpes the Eye in darkeneſſe, when it may not ſee; and ſhall the Eye and Hand of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Soule, be againſt other, or not helpe one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in neede, in one thing only needfull, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaluation of ſoule and body eternally. Is not the Soule more worth then the Body? Is not the ſight of the Soule more worth then the ſight of the Body? Is not ſpirituall things more worth then bodily
<pb facs="tcp:19510:10"/> things? if the Eye of the Body bee ſo excellent, and the more if it be ioyned with the hand, how excellent is the Eye of the Soule, well exerciſed together in the worke of the Miniſtery, and of our owne ſaluation? If naturall gifts bee ſo excellent,<note place="margin">What is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the hand.</note> how excellent are the diuine gifts of Gods holy Spirit? What ſhall all the outward ſenſes profit vs? If the windowes of the Soule be blind, what ſhall the knowledge of God and of his Creatures profit the ſoule if there bee no practiſe, but to be beaten with many ſtripes? doth not the ſaluation of the body depend vpon the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule? doth not all the ſtedfaſt ſtanding of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, depend vpon a moment of tranſitory; time well ſpent, in knowledge, and doing the will of the Lord? and namely to vs of the Miniſtery, that muſt thereby ſaue our ſelues and others; muſt our eye bee tyed to ſee, and our hand to fill the miniſtration we haue receiued of the Lord; what ſhall wee doe then to obey this admonition? behold with our eies, fill with our hands, the miniſtery we haue receiued of the Lord; ioyne practiſe and vſe, with knowledge and ſtrength continually, we muſt neuer turne our eie from our worke to behold vanitie, with <hi>Lots</hi> wife; but like <hi>Paul,</hi> haue our eyes on the worke before, and not on things behind; we muſt not take our hand from our worke till it bee full and compleate like <hi>Bazaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab</hi> building the Tabernacle that did not take away eye,<note place="margin">Numb. 3.24.</note> hand, or foote, till the Tabernacle was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Leuits are compared to Souldiers ſeruing as in warfare in the Miniſtery,<note place="margin">Sam. 1.9 9.</note> that they might ſee, and fulfill the ſame; the Prophets were named Seers, from ſeeing, and Gods, from doing the worke of the Lord; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was made a Watchman,<note place="margin">Iſai. 31.6. Iſai. 62 6. Iſai. 27.6.12.6</note> to tell the things that they ſhould ſee, concerning the deſtruction of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and to ſtand continually vpon his watch Tower, both day and night, and did ſee but the figures of the
<pb facs="tcp:19510:10"/> armies, whereby <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> ouercame <hi>Babylon,</hi> how much more, muſt we ſtand on our watch towre, to ſee <hi>Babylon</hi> fall, that Romiſh idoll; enemie vnto Chriſt, and the children of God, gathered together in the holy Citie.<note place="margin">Exod. 31.1.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt behold the forme of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and to whom it is to be committed; and like <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubabel,</hi> his beholding, till the laſt ſtone bee laid in the ſecond Temple. In deſpite of enemies,<note place="margin">Zach. 4.9. Geneſ. 41.41.</note> ſhall <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and ſee, that blacke polluted Countrie of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and fore-ſee, as hee did, what things were profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and what were hurtfull: and ſhall not wee behold, and fulfill the Miniſtration of the Holy, and lightſome Land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od dwelling in the middeſt thereof.<note place="margin">Zach. 2.11.12.</note> The Lord ſpeaking after the manner of men, declares that his Church is euer before his eyes, watching, and looking vpon it, and in this reſpect, it is ſweete vnto vs, and in this place he commands, that it ſhould neuer bee out of our ſight; like <hi>Paul</hi> in ſpirit at <hi>Colloſſe,</hi> in <hi>Phrigia</hi> beholding their ordour: Chap. 2.3. Albeit, in body in <hi>Italy,</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> in bonds;<note place="margin">Iſai. 21.21.</note> O Lord I how ſweete a ſight ſhould it be vnto vs, ſleeping, and waking, when we ſee the image, and care of Gods holy Church before our eyes, in her garments of beautie; the glory of the Lord ſhining vpon her, rather then in her mourning weed, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with the thicke cloud of his wrath: O Lord God, if we would ſee, and fill our Miniſterie, how might the Church bee edified, and her enemies deſtroyed? like <hi>Moab</hi> diſpairing of their men and gods. Thus much for the admonition in generall: the Lord open our eyes to ſee, and our hands to fill the Miniſtration, which wee haue receiued of the Lord</p>
            <p>The reaſon followeth in theſe words: <hi>Which thou haſt receiued of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus, the Authour of the glorious Goſpel,<note place="margin">Sixe points in the reaſon.</note> hath opened thine eyes, and ſilled thee with his holy Spirit, and committed vnto thee a part of the worke of
<pb facs="tcp:19510:11"/> his Miniſterie, and grathering together of his Saints; vpon condition, that beholding, and fulfilling the ſame, thou mayeſt receiue an euerlaſting Crowne of Glory, if not, to be baniſhed from his preſence for euer; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee, and fulfill thy Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>The generall reaſon, is full of ſingular arguments, all arguing, and proouing neceſſarily our faithfulneſſe, in the worke of the Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>The arguments are ſixe.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label> The firſt, is the inſufficiencie of <hi>Archippus</hi> himſelfe, to whom this worke is committed;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.12.</note> Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but an carthen veſſell, vnable of thy ſelfe to thinke a good thought, and yet allowed, and put in credite, and made powerfull by the grace of God in thee, then ſtirre vp, and neglect not the gift that is in thee; but ſee, and conſider, fulfill, an lend thy Miniſtration: <hi>Paul</hi> thankes the Lord, that hee made him ſtrong, and put him in the Miniſterie;<note place="margin">Amos 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> conſidering that it was not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor of mans inſtitution that hee Propheſied, but of the Lord that had taken him from the ſheepe; Was bold to ſee, and fulfill his Miniſterie, in deſpight of all his enemies at <hi>Bethel,</hi> in the Kings Chappell.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label> Secondly, the power and authoritie of the cheife Paſtor, and Authour of this Goſpel and Miniſtration, is the Lord Ieſus, who is Prince, and Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernor of his Church, in whom all the fulneſſe of the God-head dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth fully: The good ſhepheard that knoweth all things, hath put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Archippus</hi> in the Miniſterie, albeit, not immediatly, but me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iatly, by the ordination of the Church: <hi>Paul</hi> vſes this argument to mooue <hi>Timothie</hi> to bee faithfull, as wee ſhould all bee, becauſe the Lord Ieſus is the Authour thereof; therefore let vs ſee, and fulfill our Miniſtration, which wee haue receiued of the Lord.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the excellent worthineſſe of that ſo preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a thing put in his hand to bee kept,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.14.</note> that is the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:19510:11"/> Goſpel of the bleſſed God; thou haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receiued this great Myſterie of godlineſſe, and the Goſpel of Gods grace, to declare it perfectly, and fully to the world</p>
            <p>But let v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſee, and conſider the glory of the Goſpel, by <hi>Pauls</hi> owne compariſon of a treaſure; and <hi>Dauids</hi> golden treaſure: Gold hath ſixe properties, wherefore the word of God is compared to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, gold of all other mettélles, hath not onely a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſweete ſmell, but pleaſant in taſte, and cordiall;<note place="margin">Gold compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Goſpel in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e properties.</note> euen ſo the word of God is ſweeter then the hony, or the hony combe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, gold taketh no ſoile, neither doeth it foule <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> any thing, for it is fatneſſe that defileth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s burnt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.7. Pſal. 19.72. 1. Pet. 1.7. Pro. 8.10.15.</note> as all that are mixed therewith: ſo Gods word is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gold, ſeuen times tried in the fire, and makes our ſoulos cleane from the ſtaine of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, gold is the heauieſt of all mettalles, ſo the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> word is of moſt weight, yea, all the world is lighter then vanitie, in reſpect of this our glorious Goſpel, whereof we are now Miniſters</p>
            <p>Fourthly and fiftly gold, is <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teniſiſsimum; &amp; tenaciſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> moſt thine, and moſt tough,<note place="margin">Iſai. 40.5.</note> and therefore is drawne in greateſt length, and in greateſt breadth; ſo Gods Word, is as long, and as broad, as Eternitie it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, gold is not conſumed by fire, yea, although it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> be melted with lead many dayes, becauſe it hath no fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to burne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; ſo Gods word, is able to abide any fiery triall, and not to bee conſumed; but notwithſtanding, all this excellencie of gold, and although it were ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times tried in the furneſſe, yea, that it is leſſe thou nothing in reſpect of Gods words; for lay quicke-ſiluer vpon gold, and it will breake it all in peices, but it is not ſo with Gods word, no ſlippery ſliding, earthly ſtinking wiſedome, or preceptes of men; ſhall haue any ſtrength againſt it, albeit they prooue themſelues from
<pb facs="tcp:19510:12"/> time to time, cunning, and craftie Alchimiſtes in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, in melting brimſtone with it, which in deede conſumeth gold into droſſe; conſider then, the ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able worthineſſe of the Treaſure, which is the Goſpel of Gods grace, and thou ſhalt neuer ceaſe to ſee, and fill, the Miniſtration, and diſpenſation of this glad tidings of ſaluation. <hi>Paul</hi> knowing the greatneſſe of this worke, and the worth of it, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour himſelfe to fill the ſame, for hee ioynes theſe thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> arguments together.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is allowed of God, that the Goſpel ſhould bee committed vnto vs; ſo wee ſpeake not as they that pleaſe men, but God, which approoueth our hearts, for exhortation was not by diſceit.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1. 4, 5, 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor by vncleanneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by guile, but as we are allowed of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ment. Math. 24 50.</note>The fourth argument in this reaſon, is the word Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, thus amplified in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. to the 24. The vocation of Paſtors, is a ſeruice, and a ſtewardſhip, wherein wiſedome, and faithfulneſſe is required; <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> is as Chriſts ſerua t, and ſteward of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, working with him in his husbandry, with feare and trembling, doing the will of the Lord, not with eye ſeruice,<note place="margin">Zach. 3.9.</note> although with eye ſeruice; for God ſeeth perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the al-ſeeing eyes of his prouidence, but cheife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his holy Church, which is euer before his eyes; and therefore thou muſt doe in thy Miniſterie, as alwayes in the preſence of the Lord, and this dutie is taught vs by our name: for wee read in a dialogue where it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, who excelleth in feeding a ſtocke of ſheepe? Anſwere is made,<note place="margin">Plato <hi>in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt. Note</hi> Pſal. 21.1, 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſhepheard, for the name is taken from the office, hee therefore that fulfilleth not the one, cannot challeng the other; and the neceſſitie of this conſequent, was to <hi>Dauid</hi> an occation of great comfort, for calling him his ſhepheard, hee triumphes in it, and giues a reaſon, why hee can lacke nothing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
<pb facs="tcp:19510:12"/> God will ſeed him in greene paſtures: therefore Chriſt ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> feede my ſheepe; whereupon Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Paſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mente, paſce ore, paſce opere,</hi> feede with prayer, feede with preaching, feede with a good life, theſe doe well together, but being a ſunder profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth little.</p>
            <p>The fift argument,<note place="margin">S. Argument.</note> is the conſideration of the Church of Chriſt, bought with his owne blood, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou art made a Miniſter, for ſlocke, and ouerſeer, Church, and Miniſterie, are relatiues:<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Archippus</hi> thou art Paſtor ouer the ſlocke, and Miniſter of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, therefore ſee and fulfill thy Miniſterie:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth the ſame reaſon in his admonition to the Miniſters of <hi>Epheſus</hi> face to face, and he puts all theſe reaſons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his owne perſon, ſaying, whereof I am a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, to wit, of the Church, according to the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of God, which is giuen to mee, to you ward, to fulfill the Word of God, euen the Myſterie hid ſince the beginning of the world, yea,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.8.</note> we muſt looſe our liues for our ſlockes, if that the Lord bring vs to that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an triall.</p>
            <p>The ſixt and laſt particular argument,<note place="margin">6. Argument</note> is the reward to them that haue receiued this Miniſtration, honour, or diſhonour, ſaluation, or perdition, according as we ſee, and not ſee, fulfill, or not fulfill the ſame in the right manner, which doing, the reward ſhall bee the Crowne of glory: This argument is not expreſſed, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; for <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes in this ſhort admonition, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the Epiſtle written from <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicea,</hi> &amp; commnds the <hi>Colloſsians</hi> and <hi>Archippus,</hi> to read the verſe before my Text, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding namely, the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> where in all the duties of Paſtors are laid ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This argument made <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, woe vnto mee, if I preach not the Goſpel: if glory bee an argument to mooue ſeruants to bee faithfull; much more vs of the Miniſterie; if it doe mooue all Chriſtians to be faithfull, and to be where
<pb facs="tcp:19510:13"/> Chriſt is, how much more, ſhould it mooue the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie to bee faithfull in their calling, for it ſhall bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at the day of iudgement,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3.25. Iohn 12.26.</note> albeit, ſome haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and caſt out diuels in the name of Chriſt, except it be done in the right manner fully.</p>
            <p>In a word then, wouldſt be a Miniſter of Chriſt, then thou muſt firſt ſee farre off, and ſee all things, ſee exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely, ſee incontinent, ſee and diſcerne all things: See diuine without paine; and that which is more, the eye muſt ſee thy ſelfe and God that is inuiſible, thy hand muſt handle all things, and trie all things with the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of trueth, and hold faſt that which is good becauſe the Lord holdeth the Saints,<note place="margin">Reuel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> like the Startes in his right hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Archippus</hi> muſt then ſee, and fulfill his Miniſterie, becauſe hee is made ſufficient of the Lord, as a Miniſter to manifeſt the ſecrets of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Kingdome, and that in great wiſedome, and faithfulneſſe; and if he ſee, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his Miniſterie, the Lord will bee with him, here and hence foorth hee ſhall be with the Lord for euer: this is <hi>Pauls</hi> admonition to <hi>Archippus</hi> and all Miniſters, let this admonition and reaſon thereof, bee as a ſtoneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our eyes, like the precepts of the Law, let it bee written in capitall letters, that a man that runneth by may read it;<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.2.</note> like <hi>Abak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> viſion, let it bee written as deepe as wickedneſſe was written, with the penne of Irone,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 10, 11.</note> and point of a Diamond vpon the tables of the Iewes hearts, and hornes of their Altars: Let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what ioy, or ſorrow, ſhall be at the laſt day, and till that day come, Gods mercie is vpon good Miniſters, ſeeing, and fulfilling their Miniſterie, and Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon idoll ſhepheards,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.17.</note> theeues, and murtherers, robbers, and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elings, and negligent Miniſters, with darkened eyes, and withered hands, without Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if they haue it, it were better for them to bee without it; if wee did conſider theſe things ſincerely,
<pb facs="tcp:19510:13"/> would we not behold &amp; fill our miniſterie better then we doe, albeit many doe well: Would we faint or be broken with euils as the originall word ſignifieth, proceeding of the people, or of our ſelues; the people are commanded to obey vs that watch ouer their ſouls,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.13.</note> which were good for both; ye are commanded to giue vs double honour, but yee giue vs not ſingle; yee are commanded to reuerence our perſons for our workes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, but wee are contemned; and ſome are reſpected, not ſo much for their workes, as for their perſonage ſake. The people ſhould haue order and diſcipline,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.5.</note> like the <hi>Collosſians,</hi> for the which <hi>Paul</hi> reioyceth to behold their order, and ſtedfaſt faith in Chriſt;<note place="margin">Note.</note> but ſome haue no order, but doe refuſe wholeſome doctrine: Yet we muſt not faint, <hi>Tu, ne cede malis, ſed contra audentior ito,</hi> what, ſhall wee giue ouer, for the euels that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede of our ſelues, againſt our ſelues? albeit wee are caſt downe, yet wee periſh not: In all theſe a afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wee muſt be more then conquerours, for euerie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where wee muſt beare about, the dying of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that the life alſo of Ieſus, may be made manifeſt in our mortall bodies, as the Poet ſaith,</p>
            <q>Sepe Jouis telo quercus aduſta viret.</q>
            <p>Would the Prieſts of <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid. Triſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Eleg. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> in the Kings Chappell and houſe of the Kingdome, labour to bring <hi>Amos</hi> in diſgrace, would wicked <hi>Shemaiah</hi> call <hi>Ieremie</hi> a rauer,<note place="margin">Ierem. 29.</note> or one out of his wits; ſhall wee by euill example, cauſe the people to contemne the ſeruice of God; like the ſonnes of hell?<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.17.24.</note> ſhall wee let the falſe Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell vs, for Labour, Learning, Zeale, Free-preaching, Grace of ſpeech, Diligence in ſeaſon and out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Wherefore ſhould the Miniſterie, which is greater then greatneſſe it ſelfe, appeare vnto vs, as little as <hi>Zoar</hi> vnto <hi>Lot,</hi> and yet his great place of refuge? Who would make account of honour,<note place="margin">Note.</note> or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, honour, life, or death, pouertie, or riches, ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:19510:14"/> wee may ſee, and fill, our Miniſtrie with ioy.</p>
            <p>Thus beloued, I haue run ouer the interpretation of this text bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fely, with the language of <hi>Canan,</hi> with ſome intermixed obſeruations: And fearing, my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer interpretation ſhould ſeeme ſomewhat obſcure, I will now drawe to a populer exhortation, which is moſt conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nient for theſe times wherein we line; where there is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e knowledge then ſanctification.</p>
            <p>According to my ordinary forme, I ſhall firſt gather a generall obſeruation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t downe three poſitiue groundes of Diuinitie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing from my text, for information of your vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall come to the doctrine, which ſhall be done in forme of propoſition only.</p>
            <p>The Miniſtrie that <hi>Paul</hi> requireth <hi>Archippus</hi> to ſee, and fill,<note place="margin">Actes 20.24.</note> is euen the ſame he ſpeakes of, where he takes this admonition vnto himſelfe; <hi>But I paſſe not at all, neither is my life deare vnto me, ſo that I may fulfill my courſe with ioy, and the Miniſtration I haue receiued of the Lord Ieſus, to teſtifie the Goſpell of the Grace of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Generall Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations.</note>Two things then, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> owne example this admonition requires in <hi>Archippus,</hi> and all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in their Miniſtrie, the worke do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and the right manner of doing; the worke, to teſtifie the Goſpell of Gods grace:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.13.</note> The right manner is in two poynts, firſt, the ſpeech, next, the affection of the minde; whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.19, 20</note> ſpeech, not in the words of mans wiſdome, but in the wiſdome of the holy Ghoſt, comparing ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things,<note place="margin">1 Theſ 2.5.</note> with ſpirituall things; not in ſwallowing ſpeeches,<note place="margin">2 Tim 1.3.</note> but in ſpirituall power, to ſpeake not as they that pleaſe men,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but God that trieth the hearts, not in ſoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll fables, but in wholſome words; for this cauſe, <hi>Paul</hi> deſires the <hi>Collosſians</hi> to pray for him, that God wold open vnto him the doore of ſpeech and vtterance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 2.2.</note>The generall diſpoſition of the mind, is, that we lay
<pb facs="tcp:19510:14"/> aſide all deſire and ſhew, of humane wiſdome and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, only to reioyce in the knowledge of Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</p>
            <p>The particular affections of the minde, are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. Care of the flocke, willingneſſe, and readineſſe of mind, deſire by example to edifie, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, confidence in God, loue of Chriſt and his Sheepe: to giue freely without reſpect of ſilthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre; with loſſe of life to perſeuere vnto the end, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue our Miniſtery vnto Chriſt to our conſcience, and vnto the conſcience of the flocke. The Prophets and Apoſtles put theſe Precepts in vſe and practiſe: for <hi>Paul</hi> and his fellowes in affection and good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, they preach to vs not onely to deliuer vnto them the Goſpell of God, but their owne liues alſo.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> This patterne for ſpeach and affection <hi>Paul</hi> committed to <hi>Timothie.</hi> The Leuites in their Miniſtery,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.1.</note> which were to ſerue the Prieſt in the Tabernacle,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and to beare the ſame from place to place, which laſted but for a while, had Ouerſeers and Watchmen, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8.26. that they might ſee and fill their Miniſtery: the Leuites had fiue yeares Apprentiſhip, when they came firſt to ſerue; but when they came to fiue and twentie yeares of age, they were numbred with the reſt, and were bound but to ſoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> till thirtie yeares onely. Then they muſt begin to execute their Office fully,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.1, 3.</note> that they might ſee and fill their Miniſterie. The Prieſtes and Prophets had their celles neere vnto the Tabernacle, that they might ſee and fill their Miniſtery: but yet the Leuites muſt not looke vpon the holy things, before the Prieſt had conſecrated them, vnder the paine of death: but <hi>Archippus</hi> muſt vncouer and behold the holy things of God,<note place="margin">Tremel. in Numb. <hi>5.20.</hi>
               </note> and cauſe others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o behold them alſo, vnder paine of death. Muſt his eye bee ſatisfied with ſeeing, and his hand with filling his Miniſtery. I thinke not. Muſt we forget Saint <hi>Cyprians</hi> admonition, <hi>Sit Lectio aſsidua vel
<pb facs="tcp:19510:15"/> oratio,</hi> be euer reading or praying? Muſt not hee haue his eye, looking vpon <hi>Pauls</hi> paterne to <hi>Timothy,</hi> Of wholeſome wordes with faith and loue in Ieſus Chriſt. The Prophets that were called Seers, from ſeeing, had not the light and ſight to ſee and handle as we: for <hi>J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> propheſied that the Sunne ſhould bee made ſeuen times brighter; which is now in the Chriſtian Church fulfilled, which Sunne ſhall neuer goe downe: how muſt we ſee, how muſt wee fill the miniſtration of things ſo excellent and viſible, that euen the difficulties and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence are publike? praiſed be the name of our God for the ſame continually.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of diuinitie.</note>Now I come to the poſitiue grounds of Diuinitie, and then to the Doctrine briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cui.</note>We haue heere three things to marke: firſt, <hi>Cui,</hi> to whom is this Miniſtery giuen and concredite, to diſpoſe oft fully.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In qua.</note>Secondly, <hi>in qua,</hi> wherein this Miniſtery doth conſiſt, and the limits of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A quo.</note>Thirdly, <hi>a quo,</hi> from whom is this our Miniſtery. <hi>Je is,</hi> ſaith the Text <hi>from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fyhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>This Miniſtery was giuen to man: for when God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended vpon hye, hee led captiuitie captiue, and gaue gifts vnto man, and that to foure ſorts of men: Firſt, Prophets. 2. Euangeliſts. 3. Apoſtles. 4. Paſtors and Miniſters now vnder the Goſpell, which ſhall continue vnto the end. I thought to haue ſtood vpon this laſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe them ouer.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is, to ſee wherein this Miniſtery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts; you heard it was in ſeeing and filling, that is, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and practiſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u muſt know God, Creator of all things. 2 Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deemer. 3. The Holy ghoſt as S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tifier, both in eſſence,<note place="margin">1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>antae.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>face, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>butes; <hi>Quantae maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vt timea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quamae dignitates vt adores, quanta be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> satis vt in ſe ſperes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:15"/>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Know thy ſelfe in three things.</note> thou muſt know thy ſelfe to bee a good Chriſtian, and firſt <hi>quantae fragilitatis,</hi> Secondly, <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vilitatis.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>quantae Iniquitatis:</hi> Thou muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be learned, which learning muſt haue theſe vertues. Firſt, <hi>Sapientia coniunctiua:</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">Sixe things.</note> 
               <hi>Iuſtitia diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Patientia charitatiua:</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia ſanetiua:</hi> Fiftly, <hi>Temperantia regulatiua:</hi> Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Perſeuerantia perfectiua:</hi> Thou muſt alſo be a good Miniſter, for if thou bee not a good Chriſtian firſt,<note place="margin">Math. 6.8. Act. 15.9.</note> thou ſhalt neuer be a good Miniſter of the Goſpell, which is thy miniſtration; to be a good Paſtor thou muſt bee able to ſtand before God; now there is no ſtanding before God, but in purity of heart; marke then that the heart is onely purified by faith;<note place="margin">To ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou muſt labour by ſenſe &amp; feeling to know the courſe of Gods dealing with thy ſelf, for if thou canſt not preach by experience, thou ſhalt neuer preach with power, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the conuerſion of Gods people.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing thou muſt doe,<note place="margin">Nam ſecunda capacitatem, audientiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenda ſunt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, &amp; pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d &amp; ſubti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lia, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is to preſent thy worke before God: Firſt, thou muſt know the nature of people, if they bee in the Family of Faith or not: Secondly, if they be ignorant with knowledge, as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> thy dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is told then in the third to <hi>Titus:</hi> If they bee <hi>Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> thy duty is to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d thee in the perſon of <hi>Himineus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> to theſe extreamities: Fourthly, if they bee ſimple and ignorant, then thou muſt be, firſt meeke, ſecondly gentle, thirdly patient; ſo thou muſt bee all to all men,<note place="margin">Gregor p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 9.</note> that thou mayeſt win ſome to Chriſt: therefroe <hi>Gregory</hi> ſalth, <hi>alliter monendi ſunt proterui, at qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alliter puſillanimus,</hi> the one in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the other in iudgement.</p>
            <p>The third things is this, that wee m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt know our Miniſterie to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> worke, for when we know the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u we muſt work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Miniſtery according<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y: That this oat Miniſtery is a worke, <hi>Paal</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beſeech you brethren to know them
<pb facs="tcp:19510:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19510:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19510:17"/> which labour among you, and are ouer you in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Our worke in two things. 1 Tim 3.17. The deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a good miniſter. Iohn. 7.16. 1 Cor 11.23. Ier. 14.1. To rule well<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> three things. Ier. 1.17. 1 King. 22.14.</note>This worke is in two things, Firſt doctrine; Seond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouernement, <hi>Let the Elders that rule well bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy of double honour, eſpecially they who labour in the Word and doctrine:</hi> So, to be a good workman, is to rule, &amp; to labour well in the Word, and not to preach our ſelues, but Chriſt Ieſus the Lord.</p>
            <p>To rule in the Lord thou muſt doe three things; firſt thou muſt deliuer nothing but that thou haſt receiued of the Lord, for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>my doctrine is not mine, but his that ſent mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thou muſt deliuer his whole meſſage, with-holding n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thing; therefore God ſaith to <hi>Jeremie, Speake vnto them, all that I command thee, be not diſmaied at their faces, leaſt I confound thee before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in deliuering his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſage as Gods Word, therefore <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 4 21.</note> 
               <hi>If any man ſpeaks let him speake as the Orracles of God:</hi> to doe this, is firſt required gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, as <hi>Titus</hi> 2.17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Authority. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Sinceritie: therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>for we are not as many,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>which corrupt the word of God, but as of ſincerity, but as of God, in the ſight of God, ſpeake we in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A quo.</note>The third generall point is, to know from whom we haue this miniſtration, my Text ſaith, it is from the Lord: Let vs firſt conſider if this power bee from the Father only, or the Sonne only, or from the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Chriſt Lord of his Church.</note> or from all conioynctiue; that this Miniſtery is not from the Father as Creator, neither from the Son as <hi>ab aterno cum Patre,</hi> or the Holy Ghoſt; but this our Miniſtery vnder the Goſpell is only from Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.7.</note> as redeemer of the World, God and Man, manifeſt in the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh: for this <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith of the increaſe of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment and peace there ſhall be no end;<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 1.11.32.1.</note> more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſee <hi>Luke,</hi> who ſaith <hi>and he ſhall raigne ouer thee
<pb facs="tcp:19510:17"/> houſe of Iacob for euer, and of his kingdome ſhall be no end:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 18.</note> therefore hee ſaith, <hi>my Kingdome is not in this world,</hi> thereby ſignifying vnto vs the ſpirituall gouernement that is in Chriſt and his members the Church, to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>In this Monarchie of Chriſt, conſider theſe things;<note place="margin">9 Points to be conſidered in Chriſts Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchiall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</note> Firſt, his Throane; Secondly, his Kingdome, wherein yee ſhall ſee the King in his Kingdome; Thirdly, yee ſhall ſee his enemies; Fourthly, his Subiects; Fiftly, his Lawes; Sixtly, his Authoritie; Seuenthly, the place of his Kingdome; Eightly, the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his Kingdome, and the Kingdoms of this world, the laſt point is of the continuance of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Firſt then wee haue to conſider theſe two generall grounds: Firſt, temporall gouernours haue the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of externall conctiue iuriſdiction, and matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereto.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, that the power of the Church is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from Chriſt the Mediatour, giuen vnto all, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ar. </seg>1</label> by ordination; this is confeſſed not only by ſome of vs, but by the Fathers and Popiſh writers alſo. <hi>Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture in</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. d.</hi> 17.9.1. <hi>Auguſt Triumphus lib. de poteſt Eccleſ. Ioh. Gerſon lib. de poteſt. Eccleſ. Conſid.</hi> 1. <hi>Cardinall Cuſanus l b. de Cathol.</hi> 2 <hi>Cap</hi> 13. <hi>Cardinall Cantarenus tract de Eccleſ. poteſt. pontificis Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Rom. pont. Cap.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Firſt then we haue to conſider,<note place="margin">The nature of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> what this Throne is; Secondly who hath it; Thirdly, who giues it to Chriſt the Lord. Firſt, this Throne is the Throne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> not that materiall Throne, wherein <hi>Dauid</hi> fate in Iudgement, but a Typicall Throne; for <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe was a Figure of the Meſſias, King of the Church, <hi>but they ſhall ſerue the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 30 9. Ezec. 34.23.24</note> 
               <hi>and Dauid their King: Dauids</hi> Kingdome was a Figure of Chriſts Kingdome, which was reuealed by his Law from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb facs="tcp:19510:18"/> and not by men; much more then is there a full reuelation of Chriſts gouernment;<note place="margin">Hoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4. Note. Hoſe. 9.7.</note> for as none had power to giue Lawes to <hi>Dauid,</hi> much leſſe hath any man power to giue Lawes to Chriſt, to rule his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Who ſhall learne him wiſedome?<note place="margin">Col. 1.16.</note> it is to pull from his Throne, by the imperfection of his Lawes; he is King ouer all by Creation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.5.</note> but King of <hi>Dauids</hi> Throne by donation: to make this plaine, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is taken for the vniuerſall gouernment ouer all his Creatures;<note place="margin">Mat. 18.17.</note> the Kingdome of God in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Act 14.16.</note> is that manner of gouernement which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſeth by the Son in the fleſh, towards his Church, in gathering together of his Saints, fully by his blood and ſpirit,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4 14.</note> defendeth his Church, and ſubdueth all his enemies: this Kingdome is diſtinguiſhed in two ſorts of gouernement, the one is in the Kingdome of grace, the other in the Kingdom of glory; In the firſt, it is by his word and ſpirit; in the other we ſhall haue imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate glory: in the Kingdome of grace wee ſhall haue our coniunction with the Father through the Sonne, by faith wrought by the ſpirit in the Word, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the inſtruments thereof,<note place="margin">Epheſ 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Iohn 3.2. Heb. 20.23. Col 3.3.</note> and diſcipline, which is the band and hedge about the Vineyeard, giuen by the King to his Church, in the Kingdome of Glory we ſhall haue communion with God, by the eſſentiall word.</p>
            <p>This matter I thought to haue ſtood vpon, by reaſon it hath not bin handled by many, which wold take me many Sermons to vnforld;<note place="margin">This matter ſhall be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led elſewhere.</note> therefore ſeeing the time hath ouertaken me, Ile leaue this matter to your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration: And now to the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in the former voiſe, inioyneth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Epiſtle, that it ſhould bee read in the Church of <hi>Coloſſe</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> yet here he addes, that <hi>Archippus</hi> muſt bee put in mind of his duty, that hee ſhould ſeq, and fulfill his Miniſtery, by his diligence in practiſe and preaching the word of the Lord.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:18"/>
            <p>Whereupon I gather this firſt ground of doctrine;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Doctr.</hi>
               </note> to wit, that howſoeuer the Scriptures of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to be read by thy ſelfe, or others; yet the reading of them is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot ſufficient to caſt downe the proud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inded, or to informe the ignorant,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rea hing was the practiſe of all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ata<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is.</note> or to comfort the troubled conſcience: but if wee would profit by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Word, it muſt bee taught, preached, and expounded by liuely voice in the publike Miniſtery. Therefore let no m n thinke that Reading is ſufficient in this great worke; for Chriſt was offended to ſee the people without a Shepheard,<note place="margin">Aug de Doct. Chriſt.</note> and yet wee cannot ſay but they had the Law and the Prophets read amongſt them: and if it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been ſufficient to haue the Law of God read,<note place="margin">Math. 9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. Acts 13.</note> why did not the Iewes know and beleeue in Chriſt, whom they had crucified:<note place="margin">Not.</note> for <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Scriptures did teſtifie, that Chriſt was to come,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.39.</note> which Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth. This was the forme of old: for the Law was not onely read but expounded to the p ople.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Aug C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nteſſ. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> This wee may ſee cleare in Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who comming to heare Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> preach, not for the trueth ſake, yet by Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> preaching hee was conuerted to the trueth, as hee doth confeſſe, <hi>Ad eum autem ducebar abs te neſciens, vt per cum ad te ſciens du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon of the Doctrine is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ratio.</hi> Rom. 10.14.</note> becauſe the Lord hath appointed the preaching of the Goſp ll, to be the meanes of our ſaluation. Marke then, as wee muſt haue faith, which commeth by preaching: ſo muſt our faith bee grounded on the true ſenſe and meaning of the ſame. <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to the Eunuch,<note place="margin">Actes 8.3 2.35.</note> 
               <hi>Vnderſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt? And how can I except ſome man ſhould guide mee? Then</hi> Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p <hi>opened his mouth, and beganne at the ſame Scripture, and preached vnto him Jeſus.</hi> The Word muſt bee applyed with power,<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.12.</note> for it is quicke and powerfull, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, and doth diſcerne of the thoughts and intentions of
<pb facs="tcp:19510:19"/> the heart.<note place="margin">Deut. 17.11.</note> Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayeth, According to the Sentence of the Law which they ſhall teach thee, thou ſhalt doe.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this Doctrine, is to reprooue thoſe that thinke reading of Scripture to bee ſufficient.<note place="margin">If reading bee ſuffc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, then why did <hi>Chriſt</hi> cloſe the book and make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication at <hi>Nazareth?</hi> Luke 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 28. 1 Cor. 14.13.</note> If this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion bee in a Miniſter, it is a token, thou neuer didſt ſee nor fill thy Miniſtery, but is ſtone blinde. If this opinion bee in you that are the people, it is a token you are yet in the way of Reprobation, becauſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide your ſinnes ripped vp, and your conſciences awakened from the ſleepe of ſinne. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth, If thou pray with the Spirit, thou muſt pray with vnderſtanding alſo. Let vs marke one thing, albeit thou haue neuer ſo great learning, yet thou mayeſt bee ouertaken with paſſions and infirmities, and then of thy ſelfe thou ſhalt not bee able to ſee the danger, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it bee tolde thee by others. Did not <hi>Dauid</hi> know hee had committed murther, and yet the child of God, yet hee did not riſe from his ſecuritie, vntill <hi>Nathan</hi> did apply the Sword of the Word to his ſleeping con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,<note place="margin">Note</note> ſaying, Thou art the man. By this wee may ſee how needfull it is to haue Miniſters, not onely to reade, but to apply the Word with power to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men and women; and eſpecially at this time, and in this dead age wherein we liue.</p>
            <p>I told you in the opening vp of this Text by way of obſeruation, that the people ſhould admoniſh the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of his duetie; but now <hi>Paul</hi> giueth the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion himſelfe.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label> Whereupon I gather this ſecond ground of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: Wee ſee then, albeit Miniſters haue power and authoritie in the Church of God; notwithſtanding if they be negligent, they muſt be put in mind and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of their duty, for their places doth not exempt them from other mens ouerſight, and charitable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,<note place="margin">1 Tim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which moſt bee done in lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore
<pb facs="tcp:19510:19"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>rebuke not an Elder but reproue him as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> aſſure thy ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whatſoeuer be thy dignity in the Church, I ſay to thee in the name of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that no place of dignity or honour, worldly, ſhould hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er thee in the worke of the miniſterie; all antiquitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore corruption entred in, doth cleere this point.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, becauſe our nature being corrupted, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ratio. </seg>1</label> and thereby ſubiect to ſinne, the beſt being guilty of this hath neede of admonition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Authority of the Miniſter from God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ratio. </seg>2</label> is one ouer all, and therefore all in one, and one in all ſhould admoniſh one another, to bee faithfull in the worke of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The vſe in a word, is to exhort thoſe whom God <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> hath placed in his Miniſtery, that ye would be carefull to remoue this ill, in thinking your ſelues to be aboue your brethren, yea albeit your gifts or place carrie you out in it; boaſt not, it may be God will take both from you, to thy ſhame and ſorrow.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I requeſt you in the feare of God, that <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> your loue to Chriſt and his Church would appere, not only to hold out, and put out the ignorant; but that yee would ſee and marke thoſe that walke inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt vs;<note place="margin">Note</note> and that yee would haue the courage of the Apoſtles, of making election of <hi>Mathias</hi> in the place of <hi>Judas;</hi> and that yee would thruſt to the doore the prophane Sonnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> that makes the ſacrifice and ſeruice of God to be contemned, and had in deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on daily, as wofull experience doth let vs ſee, that wil ſee, the Lord amend it.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle deſires the <hi>Coloſsians</hi> to admoniſh <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus,</hi> that he take heede to the Miniſterie that hee fulfill it, and leaue no part thereof vnperformed.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I gather this third ground of doctrine,<note place="margin">3 Doctrine</note> that it is not ſufficient for a Miniſter to beginne, and continue in doing ſome part of his Calling; but hee
<pb facs="tcp:19510:20"/> muſt accompliſh all things belonging to the ſame: he muſt not only Reade but preach, and Catechiſe, yet liue without blame in this preſent world,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.</note> which Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, we performe, if by our preaching and liuing we gaine the ſoules of men;<note place="margin">Ezech. 34.6.</note> if wee rebuke and reproue, ſuch as are obſtinate; if we comfort the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.9.</note> if we ſtrengthen the weake; heale the infirme; bind vp the broken; ſeeke what is loſt; and bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine what was driuen away;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.14.</note> by example of the good Sheapheard: as we muſt be the mouth of God to ſpeak to the people,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.9.</note> ſo muſt we be the peoples mouth to pray vnto the Lord; example we haue of this in Chriſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Lord of all power, and had power to make his Preaching profitable; yet he prayes to his Father for himſelfe and his people;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1.3.</note> thus did <hi>Paul</hi> bend his knees for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> for the <hi>Romans,</hi> yea night and day did he pray for his Scholler <hi>Timothy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the reaſon is, becauſe the Lord will not haue a lame ſacrifice, for it is abomination vnto him.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, there is a curſe pronounced againſt him that doth the worke of the Lord negligently.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>The vſe is, to reproue thoſe Miniſters that are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in any part of their calling; ſome doe preach and liue well; ſome well, and are not able to preach; ſome liue abſent for their pleaſure, when they haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient meanes to liue by their Miniſterie; ſome place o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers for them,<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but often it falls out as it did with the Iewes, that when <hi>Moſes</hi> was with the Lord, <hi>Aaron</hi> ſuffered the people to commit Idolatrie, ere he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cke againe; ſome ſo liue, as not hauing reſpect to God nor man, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Calling, and yet can ſpeake and prate, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here were ſome goodneſſe in them: it may be ſaid of them, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells a ſtory of an old man amongſt the Grecians at the Games of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympus,</hi> and finding no place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or fauour amongſt them, went to the <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>demonians,</hi> where he found things to
<pb facs="tcp:19510:20"/> his minde; the old man cries out, all the Grecians doe know what is honeſt, but the Lacedemonians only practiſe: we ſometimes proue Grecians,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.8.</note> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple practiſe: for God ſaith, they that ſhould miniſter the Law know not; we are the Salt of the Earth, yet not ſauorie; the light of the World, yet darkeneſſe: <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 37</note> make choice of ſuch a Teacher as thou mayſt admire, more hauing ſeene him, then when thou haſt heard him; for as a Godly life doth perſwade the people vnto good;<note place="margin">Lib. paſt. Greg.</note> ſo an euill life perſwadeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to euill: therefore <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, there is no man more dangerous in the Church, then he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t liues lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carries a name of ſanctity;<note place="margin">Aguſtine.</note> therefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Omnis qui m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viuit in conſpectam corum quibus propoſitus eſt, quantum in ipſo eſt occidit.</hi> Amongſt all the dangers of the world, what is in more danger then the ſoule, yea what is more precious then the ſame? yea all the world is nothing to the ſoules h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alth: this ſhould moue vs to faithfulneſſe in our Calling, which if we doe,<note place="margin">1 Pet 3.4.</note> God ſhall giue vs an incorruptible Crowne of glory.</p>
            <p>Now the argument the Apoſtle would haue to bee vſed to perſwade <hi>Archippus</hi> to fulfill his Miniſtery, is, becauſe hee hath receiued from the Lord:<note place="margin">4 Doctrine.</note> hence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this fourth ground of Doctrine. It ſhould be a powerfull and very effectuall argument, to moue a Miniſter to be faithfull in his Calling, in that we haue it from God, and not from man; therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Timo. 1.2 1.</note> 
               <hi>I thanke him that hath made me ſtrong, that is, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for he counted me faithfull, and put me in his ſeruice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon of this Doctrine is,<note place="margin">Ratio.</note> that wee hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued this Miniſtery from the Lord, therefore the Lord wil vphold vs in all temptations that may befall vs, in body or ſoule:<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.19.</note> What made <hi>Michaiah</hi> ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with <hi>Ahab, Ieremy</hi> ſo plaine with <hi>Amos;</hi> So powerfull <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and all true Miniſters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19510:21"/> bold onely, becauſe wee haue this our Miniſterie from the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But it may be demaunded, How ſhall we know, that we haue receiued this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Miniſtery from the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, if the Lord hath giuen the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> competent meaſure of gifts fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Secondly, vpon triall and examination, if thou bee foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for that Office, bee appoynted thereto by the Church, to ſerue in the worke of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three things are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ired in a Miniſter</note>Thirdly, vpon the faithfull diſcharge of thy dutie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſpenſation beſtowed vpon thee, the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e a bleſſing vpon thy labour, hauing withall a teſtimony in thy conſcience that God hath ſent thee, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe thou art the Meſſenger of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>The vſe is to teach vs, that no man ſhould vndertake the Office of a Miniſter, except it bee giuen him from the Lord: therefore euery one of you trie your ſelues in your giftes and conuerſation, then iudge of thy ſelfe accordingly; if thou be ſent to preach boldly the Word of truth,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.13.</note> or if thou preach to the world for thy ſelfe, thou art a hyreling, and not ſent of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Miniſtery is Gods, and not mans: if thou haſt not this aſſurance of God, thou haſt no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that God will bleſſe thee in thy Miniſtery, but thou muſt looke for double torment in hell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts.</note>The Text ſayth, that we haue this our Miniſtery from the Lord; then let vs learne this laſt ground of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that Miniſters haue no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bilitie or ſtrength of themſelues to performe the worke of the Lord in their Miniſteriall Function,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> except it bee giuen them of the Lord. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that of our ſelues we are not ſufficient to thinke any thing of our ſelues, as of our ſelues, but our ſufficiency is of God, who hath made vs able Miniſters.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>yſ. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.</note> Whereupon <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quid eſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fecit vs nos preſtare poſsimus ciqua mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere gerendo eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciremur accommods.</hi> Therefore Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:19510:21"/> ſaith, Without mee yee can doe nothing.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> tooke more paines then others in executing his Miniſterie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and yet hee ſaith, It is not I, but the grace of God that is in mee. For this cauſe hee ſpeakes more inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely of all Miniſters, That it is neither hee that planteth, nor hee that watereth,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note> but God that giueth the increaſe.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, in that the worke of the Miniſtery is a diuine worke, and Miniſters are but men; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, who are ſufficient for theſe things. This difficultie is in reſpect of the worke, and ſecondly, of the perſons who are deputed to that worke. The Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Miniſter is to quicken ſuch as are dead in ſinne, to raiſe vp ſuch as are fallen, to comfort thoſe that are troubled in conſcience, to ſtrengthen the weake, to encourage the faint-hearted, to confound the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; all which are aboue humane ſtrength, yea,<note place="margin">Actes 4.15. Exod. 3.4. Ierem. 1.6. Ionah 1.3. Math. 4.1. Zach. 3.1.</note> more then fleſh and blood can doe, and yet ſubiect to the like common paſsions as other men are: In conſideration whereof many haue ſought to giue ouer their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe Miniſters are oppoſed by Sathan, and this profane world.</p>
            <p>The vſe of the former Doctrine is diuers,<note place="margin">Vſus.</note> and firſt to mooue and incite all people to pray for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: for without Gods bleſsing they are able to doe nothing, but mightie through God,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</note> to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds, caſting downe imaginations, and euery high thing, that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captiuitie euery thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Math. 9.37, 38</note> to pray that the Lord would ſend out faithfull Labourers into this his Harueſt, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gathering of his Saints, vnto the great day of the Lord: and therefore the Lord ſaith, The harueſt truely is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but the Labourers are few, at leaſt, few faithfull:<note place="margin">Actes 12.5.</note> pray ye therefore the Lord of the harueſt that he would ſend forth Labourers into his harueſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:22"/>
            <p>The ſecond vſe is, to teach you who haue giftes or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſus.</hi>
               </note> not to bee inſolent to preſume aboue your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.7.</note> for thou haſt nothing whi h thou haſt not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lord. Now it thou did<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt receiue it, why doeſt thou glory, as thou did'eſt not receiue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,<note place="margin">3. Epiſtle of Iohn 9.10.</note> doe not follow the example of <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> who lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth to haue pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heminence amongſt the brethren and doth not receiue them, and forbiddeth them that would, and caſteth them out of the Church. Then wee ſee that this excellent worke is not committed to Miniſters for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> owne take onely, not for their honour, their wealth to exalt them, but that wee bee diligent in the worke of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 6.20. Luke 10.16 1 Cor 4 13. 1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 7.</note>The third vſe is, to teach you that are the people, to learne you to reſpect the Miniſters of God; for we are Chriſts Ambaſſadors: for wee exhort you in Chriſtes ſtead, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>end your iudgement, them that are worldly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded people: let not your reſpect bee to the Miniſtery for any earthly prerogatiue, as honour, wealth, dignity, friendſhip, but reſpect vs for our Maſter the Lord Ieſus, and our works ſake; for it is the power of God to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all them that beleeue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>Vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>The laſt vſe is to all in generall; Let the world iudge of vs as it will, notwithſtanding we muſt haue our eyes fixed on ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maſter that ſent vs; let the excellencie of the one, and the dignitie of the other, ſwallow vp all ignominy and iniury the world can lay againſt vs; and that we may be able ſo to doe, let vs alwayes be diligent in praying for the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, that we may fulfill our courſe with ioy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exhortation.</note>Now to draw to a concluſion, I exhort you all, but eſpecially I direct my ſpeach to you in the Miniſterie, that in the feare and loue yee haue to Ieſus your Lord, who ſent you, yee would endeuour your ſelues, that all your exhortations and preaching to others, be written downe in the lynes of your owne life, that men ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:19510:22"/> your good workes, may glorifie your heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for we muſt haue two ſorts of garments a <hi>Bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt-plate</hi> and an <hi>Ephod;</hi> the one ſhewes,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.4.</note> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou muſt haue knowledge; the other, that thou muſt haue Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to doe: and in this <hi>Breſt-plate</hi> muſt not only be written <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim,</hi> that is, Light; but alſo <hi>Thummim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.10.</note> which is perfection; n t only light of direction, but a paterne of good workes; as the <hi>Snuffers</hi> were made of Gold, ſo we muſt not only ſhine our ſelues, but purge others: we muſt not only haue <hi>Belles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 25.38.</note> but <hi>Pom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>graners:</hi> alſo, we muſt not onely ſay w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, but do well; as the Pillers of the Taberna le, ouerlaid with Gold, but inward of <hi>Shittim wood:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 39.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> therefore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, we muſt lift vp our voice like a Trumpet, for hee winds it with his mouth,<note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.1.</note> and holds it with his hand; we muſt not only Preach but practiſe, then wee lift vp our voice like a Trumpet, if wee doe not ſee this, and fulfill our Miniſtery: What ſhall wee ſay when the Prophets, Apoſtles, Fathers, yea all the faithfull Paſtors, preſent their flocks before the Lord Ieſus, at the laſt iudgement: who is to bee blamed thinke you, that there is a negligent Miniſter?<note place="margin">A good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Act. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Is the fault in Laick Patrons, which Father <hi>Lattimer</hi> did ſee and reproue in his daies? or is it <hi>Nabals</hi> in the congregation that will not helpe faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to liue, or is the fault in the Clearg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by giuing ordination to the vnworthy? or as Patrons for their friends, as the verſe ſaith.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mos eſt Prelatis prebendas non dari gratis,</l>
               <l>Sed bene nummatis vel eorum ſanguine natis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Or is the cauſe in the People that will not obey, Sonne of man thou muſt cry, if they heare or heare not;<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.11. Ier. 5 7. Ezech. 23.9.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the Drunkard with <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Adulterer with <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> the Swearer with <hi>EZekiel,</hi> the Vſurer with
<pb facs="tcp:19510:23"/> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> the Hypocrite with <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leui. 25.36.</note> the prophane world with <hi>John,</hi> and with <hi>Peter,</hi> let all know there ſhall be a Iudgement, that the people may turne from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill wayes; this muſt not be done without ſenſe, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or motion; vſing Doctrine without application, Application without zeale, like a man without a ſoule; or as an Image on a wall: If thus wee doe, it is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident token that ſome are ignorant,<note place="margin">We muſt not feare as Ezech. 3.8.9.</note> and cannot po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully preach; being ignorant, ſome are ſo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in their Miniſtery and will not; ſome are ſo feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to offend their Benefactors,<note place="margin">Note</note> and dare not; ſome are ſo wicked, and ſhould not; alas, a guiltie Conſcience ſtaies the power of our Miniſtery, and therefore the people are not conuerted: for this cauſe the Lord ſaith to wicked Miniſters,<note place="margin">Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 23.22.</note> 
               <hi>If yee had ſtood in my counſell, then ſhould yee haue turned my people from their euill waies:</hi> therefore Brethren, wee may blame our ſelues, that neither our perſons, nor our calling is regarded,<note place="margin">Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us vita a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicitur reſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur.</note> but abuſed and d ſgraced; and thought to bee the off ſcouring of the world, and refuſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and by our vnfaithfull walking in our Calling, God hath iuſtly made vs baſe, and vile, and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible in the ſight of the people; for wee are called the troublers of the State, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Flias,</hi> a troubler of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but on the other part, are wee faithfull in our Calling, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thought b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in our perſons? poore be our liuings, and diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed in this world; yet the Lord from w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſtery, ſhall reuenge our cauſe to is glory and our comfort, and their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſorrow: therefore l t v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all offence on our part that we preach not ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uat on to oth rs, and damn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelues; for as a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lical<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pe to hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but h ate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing in ſelfe <hi>Siegre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants accedat aegretus, ſi carboni extincto, adij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rbo extinctas, vel ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeto praeſictatur caecus,</hi> what ſhall they profit one another? <hi>Praetes mortem, ciuerem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,
<pb facs="tcp:19510:23"/> foneam;</hi> therefore <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, complaining of himſelfe, <hi>Vſurpaus mihi, cotis officium qui f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrum reddit ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntum, cum ſit in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lis ad ſecundum, l'ule brum depinxe hominem, Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s alioſque redigo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed perfectionis littus qui ad huc ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r in delictorum finelibus:</hi> who then is to be rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oued? the Ignorant, Negligent, Timotus, Couetous, Prophane Paſtors; but eſpecially thoſe that appeare to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tarres,<note place="margin">Reu. 13.3.4.</note> who are drawne from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and caſt vnto the Earth, by that great red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon; this did appeare to be a wonder in Heauen,<note place="margin">Note.</note> but it is no wonder now vpon Earth; I ſay then with Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugenius, Moſtroſa res eſt gradus ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; animus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifimus, ſedes prima, &amp; vita Ima,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard lib <hi>2.</hi> de conſiderat</note> 
               <hi>lingua magni loqua &amp; manus otroſa. Sermo multus, &amp; fructus nullus, vult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> grauis, &amp; actus leuis, caput canum, &amp; corvanum, faci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rugoſa, &amp; lingua nugoſa, ingens au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas, &amp; nutan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtabilitas.</hi> I cannot paſſe by you that are our flock, there is not only amongſt you, Foxes, yea little ones, who maketh their profeſſion of the Goſpell, a ſhelter and couer to their hypocriſie; who ſerue the Goſpell ſo farre as the Goſpell may ſerue your turne, for the accompliſhing of your worldly pleaſures: there is alſo Wolues among you, in ſheeps cloathing, who kill their Shepherds,<note place="margin">Quo hierophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyco notatur hereticos ſub <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iten solen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit a principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> quod ſi ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſi etur graetus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uterit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui facilius Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitae ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur. <hi>Iſa. 50.14.15.</hi>
               </note> wounding them in their good name opprobriouſly, in their bodies dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerouſly, in their ſtate, iniuriouſly, renting both their perſons, and their Parſonages from them; for now Religion is hated amongſt many, true Godlines deſpiſed, zeale abhored, ſincerity ſcoffed at, vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe loathed, and almoſt all good men had in deriſion. And therefore we may ſay that Iudgement is turned away backeward, and Iuſtice ſtandeth afarre, for Truth is fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne in the ſtreete, and Equitie cannot enter; and hee that departeth from euill maketh himſelfe a prey; yet the Lord ſaw it, and was angry.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19510:25"/>
            <p>Albeit yee will doe no duetie, neither for our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter nor meſſage ſake, yea, hardly for your owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.11, 2.</note> yet wee knowing the terrour of the Lord, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men, and beeing Ambaſſadour for Chriſt, as though Chriſt did beſeech you by vs, wee pray you in Chriſts ſtead, that yee bee reconciled vnto God. For this cauſe Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, That the Word of God muſt bee to the faithfull, <hi>Tanquam piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s hamus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, quando capitur;</hi> yee muſt, <hi>veſe toppoſcis,</hi> as <hi>Nineueh</hi> repented at <hi>Ionas</hi> Sermon. <hi>Marie</hi> ſate all the night at Chriſts feet,<note place="margin">Acts 17.</note> hearing the Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yee ſhould ſay with the good <hi>Athenians,</hi> Let vs heare thee of this matter againe: And with the conuerted Chriſtians, who being pricked in their hearts, ſayd,<note place="margin">Actes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> What ſhall wee doe men and brethren? I ſay vnto you, as <hi>Peter</hi> vnto them, I pray God it may worke the like effect, Repent and bee baptized, in the Name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, and yee ſhall receiue the gifts of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. This if you doe, how beautifull vpon the Mountaines will the feete of them bee that bringeth glad tidings vnto you. And then at the laſt day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, wee ſhall ſay with our Maſter the Lord Ieſus, in great ioy, Thoſe that thou haſt giuen mee, I haue kept them, and none of them is loſt. Then wee ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the Firmament; and they that turne many vnto righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Iohn 17.12.</note> as the Starres for euer and euer. If thus wee would ſhine, obey <hi>Pauls</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that ſeeing wee haue this our Miniſterie as wee haue receiued mercie, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e faint not, but hauing caſt from vs the cloakes of ſhame,<note place="margin">Dan 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not walking in crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling the Word of God deceitfully, but in manifeſtation of the truth, commending our ſelues to euery mans conſcience,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4 1, 2.</note> in the ſight of God. Seeing then that both Paſtour and people doe looke for the Kingdome of Heauen, where ſhall bee one Fold, and
<pb facs="tcp:19510:25"/> one Sheepheard. Let vs all labour for the teſtimonie of a good Conſcience, and Chriſtian reſolution: In life, or death, and glorie with <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.6, 7, 8.</note> I haue fought a good fight, and am now readie to bee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the time of my departure is at hand. I haue finiſhed my courſe. I haue kept the faith. Henceforth there is layd vp for mee a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe, which the Lord, the righteous Iudge ſhall giue mee at that day, and not to mee onely,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.23.</note> but to them alſo that loues his appearance. And that both Paſtour and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may bee partaker of this ioy vnſpeakable and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, I bid you farewell in the Lord: and I pray with <hi>Paul,</hi> that the very God of Peace ſanctifie you whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and I pray God, your whole Spirit, and Soule, and Body, bee preſerued blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, glorie, and praiſe, both now, and for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
